Guide to the Office of Undergraduate Admissions Records, 1911 - ongoing UA.07.09.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of Undergraduate Admissions records
1911-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Office of Undergraduate Admissions
UA.07.09.0001
1.5 Linear Feet
The Office of Undergraduate Admissions coordinates admissions for Trinity College and the Pratt School of Engineering at Duke University. Records include applications to Trinity College prior to the founding of Duke University (1911-1925), the administrative files of Admissions Director Robert H. Ballantyne (1967-1974), one file from Admissions Director Richard Steele, and a printed version of the website from 2001.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Office of Undergraduate Admissions Records was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973-1998 and 2017.
Accessions described in this collection guide: UA2017-0001.
Historical Note
There is little written record of the early administrative reporting relationships of admissions beyond the following broad outline. When the Woman's College and Trinity College were separate, the Dean of Admissions of each school reported to the University Registrar, who reported to the Vice President of the Educational Division (now Provost). Each college may have had a committee on admissions. In 1961 William Brinkley was named Director of Admissions and probably Associate Registrar at the same time. The separate Deans of Admissions reported to him. In 1967 Robert Ballantyne was named Director of Admissions, and at this time, reporting shifted from the Registrar to an officer in the Provost's Office. In 1969 he reported to the Vice Provost and Dean of Undergraduate Education, James Price. By 1975 that title had changed to Vice Provost and Dean of Trinity College of Arts and Sciences. There was a major reorganization and retirement of admissions personnel with the merger of the Woman's College and Trinity College as of July 1, 1972. In 1978 the Director of Admissions appears to be reporting to an Assistant Provost with responsibility for Admissions, Financial Aid and Registration. In 1980 an organizational chart in a University Report uses the term Assistant Provost for Academic Support Services (Admission Records, Financial Aid, Academic Systems, Placement). However, this title was not found in a University Bulletin.
Scope and Contents note
Records include applications to Trinity College prior to the founding of Duke University (1911-1925); administrative files of Admissions Director Robert H. Ballantyne (1967-1974) and one file from Admissions Director Richard Steele; and a printed version of the office's website from 2001, including a directory of the site and its contents.
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Students; Duke University -- Admission; Duke University -- History; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Admissions; Duke University. Office of Undergraduate Admissions
- Admissions Applications, 1911-1925
  - Admissions, 1911 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1913 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1914, 1916, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1918 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1919-1923 (2 of 3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Admissions, 1919-1923 (1 of 3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Admissions, 1923-1925 (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Robert H. Ballantyne Records, 1967-1974
  - Angier B. Duke Memorial Scholarship Program, 1970-1973 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Crises (student unrest), 1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence to President Knight, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Educational Administration Advisory Group, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Visits and Speeches, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Harold Lewis, 1967-1973 (Box 2)
  - Provost Group: Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence to Ballantyne, 1969, 1970, 1973 (note letter from Cheang Koon Chang, whose father was Cheang Park Chew) (Box 2)
  - "Evolution of the American Teacher," William Cartwright, 1968 (Box 2)
  - "Duke in the Seventies," undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Teddy Segal: Winning Photograph - Washington Area Photography Contest, 1972 Nov. 24 (Box 2)
  - FERPA RESTRICTED: Correspondence with President Sanford, 1972-1973 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - FERPA RESTRICTED: Athletics, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - FERPA RESTRICTED/BOT RESTRICTED: Trustees, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Richard Steele's Office - Strategy for Undergraduate Admissions, 1987-1992 (general 25 year restriction) (Box 3)
  - Videocassette (on-site) (Videotape 1)
- Website Printouts, 2001
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of a printed copy of the contents of the Office of Undergraduate Admissions website as of December 2001. It includes directory information about the structure of and files used on the site as well as approximations of how the site looked live.
  - Directory, Academic Life, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Academic Life Fact Sheet, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Apply, Financial Aid, General, 2001 (Box 4)